<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True intelligence sent from a gentleman of account Concerning, the estate of the English forces now in Fraunce, vnder the conduct of the Right Honorable the Earle of Essex. Particularly expressing vvhat hath beene doone since his departure from England, vntill the second of SEptember last, 1591.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Fabian.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14657.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848565</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1687:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True intelligence sent from a gentleman of account Concerning, the estate of the English forces now in Fraunce, vnder the conduct of the Right Honorable the Earle of Essex. Particularly expressing vvhat hath beene doone since his departure from England, vntill the second of SEptember last, 1591.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Fabian.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Wolfe] for Thomas Nelson, and are to be solde at his shop ouer against the great South doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Fabian Iohnson.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1566-1601.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13667:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13667:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <p>TRVE Intelligence ſent from a Gentleman <hi>of account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONCERNING, The eſtate of the Engliſh forces <hi>now in Fraunce, vnder the Conduct of the Right Honorable the Earle of</hi> Eſſex.</p>
            <p>Particularly expreſsing what hath beene <hi>doone ſince his departure from England, vntill the ſecond of September last,</hi> 1591.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Thomas Nelſon,</hi> and <hi>are to be ſolde at his ſhop ouer againſt the</hi> great South doore of Paules, 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13667:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vniust rumors ſecretlie diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, concerning the diſtreſſed eſtate of the engliſh forces now in France, vnder the conduct of the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of Eſſex, hath cauſed me to publiſh this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, wherein is ſet forth nothing but that which is to bee iuſtified for truth, by thoſe that were eye witneſſes of the contents thereof.</p>
            <p>And whatſoeuer is herein contained, be aſsured it is of truth, and publiſhed onely to ſatisfie the honeſt mindes of thoſe that are deſirous to know the truth and no more, of all ſuch things, as hath hitherto paſſed ſince the departure of his honour forth of England.</p>
            <p>Accept the ſame, gentle Reader, from him, who wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the welfare of thee, and them all, and ſo in curteſie leaueth thee to the reading of that which enſueth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fabian Iohnſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13667:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter ſent out of France, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly expreſſing the true eſtate of</hi> the Engliſh forces vnder the conduct of the right Honorable the Earle of Eſſex.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good cuſſen, I cannot but muſe at the ſundry vntrue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports which (as I heare) is bruted in England concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Engliſh forces now remaining in Fraunce: For controlement wherof accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your requeſt, I ſende you the truth of all that hath happened ſince our departure, to the end you may make other of your friends acquainted with the ſame.</p>
            <p>Know therefore that after the right Honorable the Earle of Eſſex, had taken his leaue of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty then lying at Greenwich, he went from thence by water to Graues-end, where being landed he tooke horſe to Douer, meane while the ſhips paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the lands end, and ſo came to Douer, wher his Honor ſoone after went aboord, who together with the whole fleete ſet ſayls for Deepe, wher we arriued on munday being the ſeuenth day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 1591.</p>
            <p>At his Honors firſt landing, all the great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance on both ſides the hauen (at Deepe) was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and the Townes men ſtood (ready ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier like) with drums, phifes and Enſignes, and in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13667:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
token of loue and ioy ſounded their Trumpets, &amp; in all curteous maner receiued him, who together with the Gouernour of the ſayd Towne, named Mounſier <hi>de Chartres</hi> marched into the Towne, where he was royally feaſted and moſt honorably entertained.</p>
            <p>After the Earle our Generall had taken order for the landing and placing of his ſouldiers, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned at Deepe about foure dayes ſpace, and after went to <hi>Arques,</hi> which is about foure miles from thence, where he encamped and muſtred vp his men, taking aduice of the ſaide Gouernour what was beſt to be done.</p>
            <p>Meane while that his Honor remained at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,</hi> hee had certaine intelligence brought him, that the Kings Maieſty was greatly buſied about the taking of <hi>Noyan,</hi> and that by meanes thereof the King coulde not eaſelye departe thence, before he had receiued full poſſeſſion of the ſayde Towne, which was perfourmed, on the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of Auguſt laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>The Honorable Earle of Eſſex our generall, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Kings good ſucces, and hauing receiued certaine intelligence from his Maieſtye, that he would meete with him at <hi>Giſors,</hi> ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thither on the one and twenty of Auguſt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with him all his horſe men, leauing his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtill at <hi>Arques,,</hi> where they continued vntill wedneſday, being the ſecond of September laſt paſt, as heareafter is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>On the 27. of Auguſt, about the number of 400. Engliſh foote men went from <hi>Arques,</hi> with two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13667:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
hundred and fifty horſe men of Deepe, theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forth at midnight towards the riuer of <hi>Some</hi> in <hi>Picardy,</hi> and went to a towne walled with mud. neare to Saint <hi>Valeri,</hi> holden by ſuch as were ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in obedience to the King, nor in league with the Leaguers. Into this towne they entred the next morning early, where they tooke the towne &amp; about three hundred horſe and wagons, which they conducted to <hi>Arques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Earle being come to <hi>Giſors,</hi> attended there for his Maieſtie, who came the next day, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Earle moſt louingly, to whom he gaue ſo great entertainment, as beſt beſeemed ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a perſonage. And firſt greatly thanking the Queenes Maieſtie of England, for her highneſſe moſt gracious and louing kindnes towardes him, and then gaue thankes vnto the Earle for his great curteſie, forwardnes, and paines taking, in attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to hazard his owne perſon in ſo tedious a iourney.</p>
            <p>After that the king had honorably entertained the Earle, according to the manner and cuſtom of this country, he departed towardes the Germaine Armie, conſiſting of eighteene thouſand both of horſe and foot, who then ſtaide about <hi>Champaigne</hi> for the comming of his Maieſtie. But the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> accompanied with the Lord Marſhall <hi>Biron,</hi> departed from thence to <hi>Pont-de-larche,</hi> where hee yet remaineth.</p>
            <p>This Towne of <hi>Pont-de-larche</hi> ſtandeth about ten mile from <hi>Roan,</hi> in like ſorte as <hi>Kingſtone</hi> ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from <hi>London,</hi> which Towne is holden for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13667:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
King, and hath a bridge ouer it as <hi>Kingſtone</hi> hath, hauing a Caſtle on the other ſide thereof, ſtanding as her Maieſties Manor of <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, which together doth now keepe the riuer, and doth cutte off all the prouiſion that can goe to <hi>Roan</hi> by water, by reaſon that the veſſels of prouiſion ſent by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, muſt firſt paſſe vnder that bridge, before it can come to <hi>Roan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The aforeſaid bootie came in verie good time, by reaſon they greatly wanted horſes and wagons for the carriage of their prouiſion, which ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtood them in great ſtead, when the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie remooued from <hi>Arx,</hi> which was on Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day being the firſt of September laſt, on which day the armie aroſe, and laded their ordinance, and ſo departed, marching towardes the place where the Generall ſtaide, being accompanied with Sir <hi>Thomas Leighton</hi> knight, who is lately landed at <hi>Deepe</hi> with great prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ordinance. To which place alſo there came ordinance from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and ſundrie other places, ſo that ſhortlie it is likely that there will be ſome notable ſeruice performed againſt <hi>Roan,</hi> when the kinges forces, conſiſting of French men, Engliſh men, and Germaines, doe meete and ioine altogether, which will bee forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God willing.</p>
            <p>God bee bleſſed for it, there is plentie of good victuals in the countrie, whereof we want not, and the ſame ſold at a reaſonable rate. A man may buie a good quarter of mutton for two ſhillinges: a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon for eighteene pence, and twentie pence the beſt. Of bread, butter, cheeſe, and fiſh there is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13667:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
Salt fiſhe is there verie good cheape. A man maye buye a good Salt fiſh for three halfe pence, which will ſerue foure men to their dinners: and of this and ſuch like prouiſion, the countrie doth bring in great abundance.</p>
            <p>And wheras the report runneth, and hath been ſpred almoſt euer ſince my Lords departure, that ſundry Captaines hath beene lately drowned through their owne wilfull negligence, and that there hath alſo many Engliſh men died out of the Engliſh Army ſince their comming ouer, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of peſtilent ſickneſſe which hath riſen amonge them: all this God be thanked is meere falſe, for neyther hath there any Captaines at all bin drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor yet any ſuch extreame ſickenes happened among our Army as is reported. For of certainety there hath not aboue ten or twelue perſons dyed by ſickneſſe at the moſte of that great multitude, and the moſt part of thoſe that haue ſo died (or are now ſicke) is ſuch as being riotouſly giuen, haue ſpent and conſumed their money at dice, or in dronkennes, and ſuch like vnmeet exerciſes, who, when they want money, run and feede on greene fruit, whereof there is great ſtore, by which means ſome doe ſurfet and fall ſicke, to the great indaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of their owne liues.</p>
            <p>Thus my good kinſman, I haue diſcouered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the true newes of all that hath happened ſince our departure from England. Other newes I haue not as yet to ſend you, but ſo ſoone as anye thing is perfourmed, you ſhall receiue certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13667:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->This one thing I thought good to acquaint you withall, whereof I know England wil be right ioyful to heare: namely, that the French king hath by Act of Parliament baniſhed the Pope from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any rule, gouernement, or authoritie within the dominion of Fraunce: and hath publiſhed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts in print concerning the ſame, throughout all his kingdome: yea he hath alſo cauſed his Buls o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to be burned before the gates of al his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Townes and places, to the great amazement of thoſe that are the chiefeſt pillers of the Romiſh Sinagogue. And thus with my harty commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to all our friends &amp; well willers in England, I committe you to the protection of the Almighty, who proſper you for euer more.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Arques <date>this 2. of September. 1591.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louing friend and nephew. <hi>Fabian Iohnſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13667:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
